Jonathan! Nancy! Jonathan!
Jonathan! Nancy!
What the hell are you doing?
Listen to me! Don't touch anything!
Maybe you missed?
- Maybe we should, uh...
- Yeah.
Before you say anything,
I know it's 5:00 in the morning,
but I need you
to build me a telemetry tracker.
What? Erica, it is--
Five in the morning.
She led with that, buddy.
I'm sorry. Who are you?
- My uncle.
- Babysitter. Babysitter.
Who is it, snookums?
It's okay, sugar lump. Go back to bed.
I'll just be one second.
Okay.
The librarian?
You get too loud in the sack,
she shush you?
Okay, listen. You and whoever you are,
this is highly inappropriate.
I will see you in class, Erica.
Dustin is in danger.
Danger? What kind of danger?
Like the life or death kind.
What do you say, snookums?
You gonna keep playing with your bookworm,
or you gonna build us our tracker
and save your star student?
Henderson!
Dustin!
Dustin. Hey. What the hell was that?
Was that the shield generator?
Did they find it?
I was wrong.
I was terribly,
catastrophically wrong.
What?
After you left, I found a journal.
Brenner's journal.
The key to destroying that wall
is in this lab,
but it is not a shield generator.
It isn't dark magic. Vecna didn't make it.
Science did.
Theoretical physicists call it
exotic matter.
A single source of energy
that is holding that giant wall together,
and I think Nancy just shot it.
How is that bad? That's why
we're here, to get through this wall.
- You are not listening!
- I am listening.
Vecna didn't make the wall.
So he isn't on the other side,
which means Holly and the missing kids
aren't either. Nobody is.
Then what the hell is
on the other side of that wall?
Why'd it stop?
Dustin, what's on the other side
of the wall?
Death.
Whoa.
Come on! Come on, let's go!
Hurry! Hurry! Hurry!
Let's go! Let's go!
Get down! Get down!
This whole time,
everything we have ever assumed
about the Upside Down has been
dead wrong.
The gate!
I can clear a path!
No, no, no!
You stay behind... stay behind me!
No! Goddamnit!
No!
No! No!
This place, the Upside Down,
it isn't another dimension.
It's not another world.
It's a wormhole.
A bridge
between two points in time and space,
between our world and another.
And if the bridge collapses?
It will take us with it.
All of us.
Go, go, go, go!
Are you okay? Are you okay? It's okay.
We're safe here.
He can't get us here, okay?
Max...
Holly!
Come on.
Holly, sweetheart.
Stop, or I'll hurt her.
I know you believe Max is your friend.
But she has tricked you, Holly.
She has corrupted your mind.
She is a liar.
No! No, you're the liar!
I saw you! I saw what you really are!
You're a monster! A disgusting monster!
Holly!
If you don't come back with me right now
and rejoin the other children,
I will have no choice but to hurt Max.
I may even have to kill her.
Then why don't you? Huh?
I'm right here.
Oh, that's right.
You're too scared of a stupid cave,
you goddamn coward!
Things have changed, Max.
There are now other ways to get to you.
And Holly?
When your new friend begins to suffer,
and she will suffer,
you can either return to me
and end her suffering,
or you can watch your new friend die.
Her life is in your hands.
Can someone please explain to me
what the hell happened out there?
We burnt out the particles.
I watched them fly up the tower.
- I mean, you guys saw that, right?
- Hard to miss.
So Will should be unplugged
from the hive mind.
- Theoretically.
- But why didn't he wake up?
How did he see Max if she's with Holly?
Is this real?
Is Vecna messing with us again?
This makes no goddamn sense!
The doctors, they never understood
why Max was in the coma, right?
What? No. Why?
Okay. Okay, okay, okay, okay.
So let's just assume for a second
that everything that Will saw was real.
- He saw Max. He saw Holly.
- Yeah, but how?
I'm getting to that. Let's say that, uh...
this is Will,
and this is Holly.
And...
uh, this, of course, is Max.
They're in three disparate locations,
the Squawk, the hospital,
and some presently unknown place
in the Upside Down. Right?
- Right.
- Yeah.
But they share one very essential thing
in common.
They're all unconscious.
What happens when Vecna captures you?
You go into a trance.
Which would look
a heck of a lot like a coma.
No wonder the doctors are so clueless.
Max was never in a coma.
She was in a trance.
Just like Will. Just like Holly.
It is hitting me
like a Whitney Houston high note.
What if their minds...
are all in the same place?
In Vecna's mind.
Imprisoned.
At least, they were.
If Will's right,
then Max and Holly
are now making a prison break.
And if they succeed,
they will return to their physical bodies,
and Max will come back to life.
And they'll have been
in Vecna's mind, literally.
They'll know everything.
They'll know where Will is.
- Where the kids are.
- They might even know what he's planning.
- That's endgame.
- The fate of the planet may very well rest
in the hands of your comatose girlfriend
and your baby sister.
It's worth one more shot, right?
- Can you drive?
- Not legally.
Good enough.
Take Joyce's car. Do not get pulled over.
Get to Max. I'll stay with Will.
Okay.
Do you remember this place...
William?
No, no, no...
- Does it... bring back...
- No.
memories?
Max, Holly...
They got away, didn't they?
Did the leg slow you down?
You think you are clever, don't you?
But remember, I am the one.
The one who invited you in.
You were my vessel.
My spy.
My builder.
Builder?
How do you think the tunnels came to be,
William?
You built them
each and every night you slept.
There is much power within you.
But make no mistake, boy.
They are my powers,
and they are stronger than ever before.
Much stronger.
Now, at last, it is time.
Time for my vessels
to lead us to a new world.
A better world.
Too bad your world will never exist,
now that Max has one of your vessels.
There are ways
to smoke a fox from its den, William.
And you are going to help me.
You are going to be my spy
one last time.
No.
Never.
The more you resist...
the more this will hurt.
Stupid.
- Hey!
- What are you doing?
Seeing if he's still out there.
- He's not.
- How do you know?
Because he knows he can't get us in here.
Let's go.
He said that things had changed,
that there were other ways.
Yeah, and he's totally full of shit.
You should know this by now.
So we're supposed to what?
Just do nothing? Accept our fate?
No, we're not accepting shit.
We're just staying alive
until we're rescued.
- Rescued by Eleven?
- Mm-hmm.
How do you know that was even her?
Unless you know somebody else
with psychic powers
who's able
to remotely infiltrate Vecna's mind,
fight him off, communicate through him
to tell us to run, then it had to be El.
Which means she knows we're here,
and she'll come and she'll save us.
Now, can you please stop pacing?
Seriously, you're starting
to remind me of your brother.
Thank you.
Why can't Henry
come in here anyway?
I don't know.
You've had two years with nothing to do.
You must have a theory.
If we're just waiting,
we might as well talk.
- This prison...
- Camazotz.
Camazotz. Sure.
It's made up of Henry's memories, right?
Including this cave.
So I figure it's like,
I don't know,
a memory that, for whatever reason,
Henry doesn't want to face.
Something traumatic.
Except there's nothing in here
that is even remotely scary, so...
maybe not.
Anyway, that's my theory.
I like it.
Thanks.
And if you're right,
maybe we can escape through this memory.
- What?
- Okay, so...
My house, your attic,
those were traumatic memories too,
and they led us out of Camazotz.
So maybe Henry's memory can too.
First of all, there's nothing in here,
as I said.
Secondly, our memories
weren't simply traumatic.
They were memories of the precise moment
that Henry stole our minds.
And he can't steal his own mind, can he?
- How do you know?
- Because that makes no sense.
And everything in this place makes sense?
I mean,
maybe there's like a...
a secret passageway or something.
Right, yes, I totally forgot
about the secret passage.
What about out there?
Sand. Lots of sand.
- You've searched it?
- Yes.
- All of it?
- It goes on for miles.
So, no.
You are not going out there.
Holly, we're staying here,
and we wait for Eleven, end of story.
I don't think Henry was bluffing
when he said
there's another way to get to you.
We have to find a way out of here
before that happens.
You coming?
Or are you gonna let
a child head into the desert unsupervised?
I take it back.
You don't remind me of your brother.
You are your brother!
Joyce?
Did someone call the funeral home?
Mike.
El!
Oh, Mike...
I'm here now.
You're okay.
I'm okay.
This is Kali,
my sister.
And this must be the famous Mike.
I don't... I don't understand.
It's a long story.
Probably best just to tell it once.
Where's the rest of our greeting party?
He's just in here.
Oh, Jesus.
How long has he been like this?
A few hours.
Do you think you can find him?
Any clue in there about how long
it takes a wormhole to collapse?
Ten minutes, maybe 20?
I thought it'd be instantaneous.
Clearly not.
- Why do you sound disappointed?
- I'm not disappointed.
- You sound disappointed.
- I'm confused.
As far as I see it,
there are two possibilities.
Either this is the afterlife,
and you and I are spirits.
- Which seems unlikely.
- Ooh.
Or Nancy didn't completely destroy
the exotic matter.
Because if she did, the walls
of the wormhole would have collapsed.
And we would have been sucked
into oblivion.
Okay, so what
are we waiting around here for?
Where are you going?
To see if I can get a damn signal
to find Nancy.
- Steve, wait.
- Let's go, Henderson.
- Wait!
- Let's go.
Steve, we don't know if it's safe up here.
You said
the exotic matter wasn't destroyed.
No, I said
it was not completely destroyed.
But it was very clearly disturbed.
We have no idea what effect this will have
on matter, space-time, gravity.
This whole building could very well be
a highly unstable,
physics-defying death trap.
It seems pretty stable to me.
Nancy, you copy? Jonathan, are you there?
Hello?
Mother of God.
Please tell me they're not up there.
No, no, no, no. No! Nancy!
Nancy! No, no, no.
Nancy!
Come on. Nancy.
Come on. Come on.
- Are you okay? Are you okay? Okay.
- Yeah. I think so.
What happened?
I don't know. I don't know.
I guess we fell.
And also clearly didn't destroy it.
Just pissed it off.
Come on. Let's go.
Let's get the hell out of here.
- Where's the door?
- Shit, shit.
It's there. Come on.
Shit!
No, no, no! Shit! Shit! No, no, no, no!
Goddamnit.
Come on!
Nancy, she didn't leave
a note or anything at the church?
No. No, nothing.
Which means they're either
a bunch of inconsiderate pricks,
or they got captured by the military.
To put your mind at ease, I am heavily
leaning on the inconsiderate prick theory.
Wait, and that flesh wall you found,
you don't think...
They got sucked into
the giant vacuum cleaner? No, I don't.
But I don't really know, Mike.
I'm as confused as you.
This whole thing, Max, Holly, this wall,
it's all gotta connect somehow,
but I can't figure out how.
It's like
there's a missing piece of the puzzle.
A big piece.
The pieces are in Vecna's mind,
and now we finally have a way to get in.
Except Jane hasn't found anything.
Oh, boy! Here comes Pollyanna
to brighten everybody's day.
She's struggling up there.
Oh, yeah?
Maybe you should give her some time.
She's getting weaker, not stronger.
So you are the expert on El, huh?
You've known her for what,
a day and a half?
Longer than you, actually.
We were raised together,
and her name is Jane.
- Jane Hopper.
- I'm just here to help.
You're just here to help.
Well, I'm sorry I'm all out of gratitude.
I thought you said
this fight was pointless.
You said this whole thing was pointless?
I never said that.
Really? It sure as shit sounded to me
like you did.
I leave you alone for two seconds with El,
and you worm your way into her head.
She's probably having trouble finding Will
because you've thrown her off track.
She was off track when I met her
because of you.
Because of your lies.
Everything I have done...
...is to protect her.
Keep telling yourself that,
but if you really want to protect her,
she needs to know the truth,
and she needs to be ready
to deal with what's waiting for her
on the other side of this.
Killing Henry won't end this.
What does that mean?
It means nothing. She's a child.
She has no idea what she's talking about.
She's talking a bunch of nonsense.
I think you know I'm not.
But just as you lie to Jane,
you also lie to yourself.
You ask why I'm still here?
I'm here to make sure
that this never happens again.
El.
El!
Hey, is everything okay?
I can't reach him. He keeps slipping away.
Well, we have plenty of food in there,
so eat, rest, and recharge your battery,
and we'll try it again.
Or...
we improve your signal.
- The tank.
- Yeah. It'll take a while to set up.
But you've gotta
recharge your battery anyway.
Plus, that thing was a pain to build,
so I'd like to get some use out of it.
- Doris, I'm gonna sign in later.
- I'm here for emotional support.
Miss Buckley! Miss Buckley!
Oh! You know what?
Hey.
- We need to talk.
- Yeah.
- Wait, Robin!
- I've gotta deal with this. Just go!
What about the plan?
Vickie.
Listen, I know you're pissed,
and you have every right to be.
- They're looking for you.
- Who is looking for me?
- Security. MPs.
- Why?
- You wanna play dumb?
- I have no idea what you're talking about.
Okay, all right, let me give you a hint.
You, Mr. Bailey's room, benzos.
Well, does it ring a bell yet?
Robin, you've gotta start telling me
what is going on with you right now.
Okay, Max, time to come home.
I think
we've been at this long enough.
We've searched
an inch of this place.
At last, you get my point.
I've spent I don't know how long
searching out here, but too long.
You're not gonna just suddenly find
something that I haven't, okay?
Did my brother ever tell you
about Uncle Eric?
Uncle Eric?
He's a metal detectorist.
Do you know what that is?
He searches for metal.
Yeah, with his metal detector.
Looking for super old treasures and stuff
that dead people have left in the ground.
Anyway, his favorite place to search is
Indiana Beach Amusement Park.
I mean, he searched there for years,
but all he ever found
was a bunch of cheap trinkets.
Then one day, he opens up the newspaper
and boom, front page,
some random tourist found a tin can
filled with gold and silver coins
worth like millions of dollars.
Right, so let me guess,
in this scenario, I'm Uncle Eric...
And I'm the tourist.
So stupid.
"M" marks the spot.
- Where are you going?
- I have an idea.
- What idea?
- I'll show you when we're closer.
- Holly!
- You said you wanted to go back.
Well, we're going back.
Guys, if you can hear us, we're coming.
I repeat, we're coming.
Steve, slow down! The higher we go,
the more dangerous it gets.
All the more reason to speed up.
We're no use to them if we're dead. Steve!
As I was saying...
Come on!
Damn it!
What are you doing?
A few floors down, it looked like one
of those soldiers cut through that door.
Watch out.
Shit! Get back!
Shit! Shit!
Oh, God!
Holy shit!
The table! Get to the table!
Now what?
Help! Help!
- Help! Help!
- Steve!
- Hey! Help!
- Help! Help! Help!
Almost ready out here.
El's gonna fix this.
She's gonna fix it.
It was my idea, Hop.
It was...
my idea for him to go in there.
I don't know. I just thought maybe,
after everything that happened,
after everything I saw him do, that...
I started thinking maybe all this time
that I've been trying so hard
to protect him,
I've really just been holding him back
by not listening to him,
not trusting him.
And so if I just...
I don't know.
If I just believed and let go,
that, I don't know,
somehow this could all work out. And...
It's like every choice
that I make is wrong.
I know.
I mean, you can push them into situations
they might not be ready for.
You can be like me,
and you can be overprotective,
and they just resent you for that.
Joyce, one of the joys of being a parent...
is that you'll have a constant reminder
your whole life
that every choice you've made
has been wrong.
It's not on you, Joyce.
It's not on you.
That looks nice.
Murray find that for you?
Yeah.
Santa Claus has good taste.
Hey. Back at the Squawk,
Kali, she said something weird
about this not being over
even if we kill Henry.
Do you know what she's talking about?
It doesn't matter.
I should warm this up.
Okay, well, if it doesn't matter,
then why was Hop so angry at her?
It's nothing, Mike, really.
- Friends don't lie.
- I'm not lying.
You're avoiding. That's a cheat.
I just want to help.
You can't help. Not with this.
Let me be the judge of that.
El, come on.
There's a lab in the Upside Down.
They're restarting Papa's program.
Trying to make new numbers.
The military?
Okay.
So, after we kill Vecna,
we destroy this new lab.
End the program. Like a side quest.
Mike, no, you don't understand.
They don't need a lab to make new numbers.
Henry's blood.
It's in me.
I'm not a monster.
I know that now.
But with me, with my blood,
they can make more monsters.
They can make more Henrys.
The military will always be looking
for you.
We've always known that.
Which is why we aren't staying in Hawkins.
When this is all over, we're leaving.
Escaping to some far off land. Remember?
Somewhere where they can't find us.
Somewhere
where there's at least one waterfall.
Mike.
This isn't like one of your campaigns.
You don't get to write the ending.
Not this time.
Maybe I don't.
But we do.
You, me, Lucas, Will, and Dustin.
Because this is our story.
And it starts with getting Will back.
Max.
You realize you don't need
your spyglass anymore? That's my cave.
Yep.
Also, the cap is still on.
Look.
Cap on.
Okay, it's very dark.
But not totally.
You see that cutout of light?
It's in the same shape
as the cave entrance.
What are the chances
it cracks in the same shape as the cave,
the cave we know Henry visited?
I think the cap is a map,
a map Henry made when he was young,
a map that'll lead us
to some kind of secret location.
We just have to get the shapes to line up.
And you think in this secret location,
we'll find what?
Henry's traumatic memory?
That. And a way out of Camazotz.
At least... that's my theory.
- I like it.
- Thanks.
There's one tiny hole
in your theory, though.
We're near the secret location,
and I've got eyes,
and I still see absolutely nothing
but more goddamn sand--
Hold on!
"M" marks the spot.
Vic, do you want
to maybe verbalize something?
It's just unclear what your face
is trying to communicate here.
I know that it's a lot to absorb,
especially all in one go.
Monsters and alternate dimensions,
and I realize that the drugging
of the Turnbows was a bit unethical--
- Okay, stop, Robin. Please, just stop.
- I tried to tell you like a million times.
No, you lied. And then you kept lying
over and over and over again.
- I knew something was wrong.
- I know! I'm sorry!
"Crazy day at work. Call you tomorrow."
"Sorry, there's another crisis
at the Squawk."
I mean, who works all night
at a radio station?
And who is stupid enough to believe that?
Apparently me, Vickie,
who's sitting at home,
waiting for the phone to ring
while you're off with your friends,
getting high.
Getting high?
Come on, Robin.
You are going through withdrawal.
You have the wrong idea.
I am not on drugs.
- Right, sorry.
- Just look at me!
You have been busy with your friends
hunting monsters!
God! All right,
maybe you even believe it yourself.
With the amount that you were clearly on,
if you just go cold turkey,
it can cause confusion,
paranoia, hallucinations...
These are not hallucinations!
Okay. So let's recap.
- There is a dark wizard...
- Uh-huh.
- ...who is stealing children...
- Yep.
- ...and putting them in a dream world.
- Right.
Vickie, the earth has split in four.
The military has taken over our town.
Is what I'm saying really so insane?
Batshit!
You wanna know
what my face is communicating right now?
- Yes.
- Anger.
But with a dash,
and it is a very, very reluctant dash,
of worry.
Because as furious
as I am with you right now,
you are not well, Robin,
and you need help.
You need serious help.
- I got a call about some drugs...
- Hang on.
Have you seen her?
Robin Buckley?
Yes, she's here. I just saw her go
into that room right there.
Vickie, I'm so sorry.
Don't.
- But I gotta go.
- Robin!
Hey!
Hey, I'm talking to you!
Buckley, stop!
Where do you think you're going?
Help!
- Help!
- Dustin!
- Help! Steve!
- Hey!
Oh, thank you.
Steve, what the hell are you doing?
That's never gonna work. Stop! Stop!
Steve, stop. I'm serious. It's not safe.
- You're gonna fall.
- It's unstable. I got it already, okay?
No, don't! Stop being an asshole!
I'm not. I'm trying to get to them!
You always try to get yourself killed,
and I can't let it happen again.
Stop being so selfish, please.
If you go on there, you're gonna die,
and I can't deal with it again.
You can't die
'cause I can't deal with it again.
Don't let it happen again.
Please. Please don't let it happen again.
Not you.
I'm sorry.
No, no, no.
- Help!
- Come on! Help! Hey!
Whoa, whoa, whoa!
Down. Get down. Get down.
- What are we doing?
- Sitting spreads our weight out.
Mr. Goldstein, physics.
We can buy ourselves some time.
They must have heard us by now.
Then why haven't they called back?
And even if they did,
what could they even do?
Something. Anything.
Yeah. Yeah.
They're not coming.
Don't say that.
You wanted honesty.
I hate The Clash.
What?
Every time you put them on,
I just try to disassociate from reality.
Yep.
I hate reading your articles.
You don't actually wanna hear my thoughts.
You just want me
to tell you they're great.
Because they are.
Most of the time.
Most of the...
Wow. Okay.
I never read Slaughterhouse-Five.
I just read the Cliff notes
and pretended I liked it.
I never read Anna Karenina.
I just read the Cliff notes
and pretended I liked it.
You are always exactly six minutes late,
and I never say anything,
but really, I wanna punch a wall.
I took your pink sweater to Goodwill.
What? I was looking for that.
You know I hate pink.
But I felt guilty afterwards
if that makes you feel better.
I flushed the last bag of
Purple Palm Tree Delight down the toilet,
and I didn't feel guilty about it after.
- Come on.
- I hate it when you're high.
I hate it when you're drunk.
I hate it most of all
when you're high and I'm drunk.
Me too.
Why do we do that?
No idea.
I never applied to Emerson.
I know.
Why didn't you ever say anything?
Why didn't you?
I'm not sure.
I just felt like I was...
doing something wrong.
Like I was going against
the natural order of things.
You know, with...
with what we've been through, it just...
You mean our shared trauma?
Yeah.
How could anyone else possibly understand?
It's like this...
this thing that...
ties us together forever.
You know?
It made me feel safe.
But also...
I don't know.
It can be suffocating.
Yeah.
That spring break,
when you were in Lenora...
I didn't really have to stay behind
to work.
I could have had Fred cover for me.
But I think that's why I stayed.
That feeling that I just...
I needed space.
Space to be with someone else?
Steve's a good guy.
He makes me laugh.
And, he has better hair than you.
Like, way better.
But no.
No, it was never like that with him.
We're just different people.
You know what he told me?
He wants six kids.
Six kids?
Six little nuggets.
That's like a Happy Meal.
But my point is...
he knows what he wants, and that's great.
But I...
don't.
And...
I guess I was hoping
I'd have time to figure that out.
- But then...
- The world split in four.
And now...
Hey...
One last confession.
A big one.
John Coltrane.
I figure that...
I've screwed up enough with you.
It'd be nice to get something right
for once in the end.
Here.
Nancy Wheeler.
Will you...
not...
marry me?
I tried to convince myself
that this would somehow
fix everything.
But it was just gonna make things worse.
Which is why it has been sitting
like a cannonball in my pocket
for the last two days.
So what do you say?
Do you accept my un-proposal?
I accept your un-proposal.
I loved you.
I love you,
Nancy Wheeler.
I love you, Jonathan Byers.
Oh my God.
Jonathan!
Oh my God!
My God.
Thank you.
I will find him.
I will bring him home.
Okay. Now remember,
if you want out of there...
Will, I'm here.
I need you to show me where you are.
Show me where you are.
Will.
Will, can you hear me?
Will, wake up!
Can I have that?
Do you think someone fell?
It... It's just a memory, right?
Nothing in here can hurt us.
Nothing can hurt us.
Just stay behind me, okay?
- But you said--
- I know what I said.
How did you find me?
He sees us. He sees us.
How does he see us?
I won't hurt you.
Please, mister, don't shoot.
Who are you?
Henry. Henry Creel. I live near here.
- Who sent you?
- Nobody sent me.
- They sent you.
- I was in the caves. I heard a scream.
They sent you!
You're just confused. You need a doctor.
Please! Please!
Holly!
Shit!
Hey, it's okay. It's okay.
Why did that man try to hurt Henry?
Hurt Henry? He was only trying to help.
- I don't know.
- Is this what made Henry bad?
I don't know. But it's over now, okay?
We have to keep moving.
You were right.
The way out of Camazotz, it's here.
♪ Be runnin' up that road
Be runnin' up that hill ♪
Max?
♪ ...make a deal with God
And I'd get Him to swap our places ♪
You are going
to spy for me one last time.
Found you.
Will. Will, it's okay.
It's okay. I'm here.
- El...
- I'm here.
El... El...
It's me. It's me.
I'm here to bring you home. It's okay.
I tried to stop him, but I couldn't.
He saw.
He saw what? What did he see?
Max.
He knows where she is now.
And he sent them after her.
They're coming for her. In Hawkins.
- El!
- El, what's up?
Are you okay?
El, what's wrong?
- Is he all right?
- Yeah.
Vecna's going to kill Max.
We have to get to the hospital right now.
Hey! Are you deaf or what?
She's in withdrawal.
- I am not.
- You know what that means?
She needs to be in a hospital,
not a prison.
Would you look at that?
She's in a hospital.
This is Hawkins, Candy Cane.
Not our first junkie.
Power outage in a hospital.
Can't be good for Granny. Not our problem.
You don't understand. We need to evacuate.
We don't need to do shit.
Keep moving, junkie.
I'm not a junkie.
If we don't get everyone
out of here right now,
we are all going to die.
There is nothing you can say
on God's green earth
that is going to keep you out of a cell.
So save your junkie breath.
- We need to evacuate.
- I actually don't need to do shit.
Holy shit!
Run!
They're not after us.
Huh? What?
Do you know another way out?
The basement. The basement!
It leads to staff parking.
Okay.
Come on, Lucas, pick up. Pick up.
Pick up. Pick up. What are you doing?
- Can those things understand English?
- No.
- Then this doesn't need to be private.
- What?
Lucas, it's Robin.
A Demo is headed your way.
Do you hear me? A Demo is headed your way.
You need to get Max out of there now.
Take the elevator.
They're on the stairwell.
We'll meet you in the basement.
Come on. Come on.
Shit.
Shit. Come on!
Goddamnit!
It's not budging.
We're just gonna have to try, okay?
Come on.
You good?
- I... I'm good.
- Okay.
- I need you to grab my hand, okay?
Whoa! Jesus!
Okay. They're coming!
- We gotta go!
- Which way?
Here! What the hell is going on?
- Here!
- How are they finding us?
I don't know,
but we gotta get out of here.
Okay. Come on.
- Come on. Let's go.
- Go, go, go.
Come on. Shut the door. Shut the door!
- Oh, shit.
- Go! Just keep going!
- Come on.
- Damn it!
We gotta go!
- The door! Open the door!
- Go, go, go!
Shit. This way, guys! Come on! Come on!
Get down!
♪ If I only could... ♪
I'm really sorry
I thought you were a druggie.
I'm sorry for lying to you for, like,
a ludicrously extended period of time.
For the record,
I wasn't lying about Enzo's.
And if by some miracle we survive this,
I am going to take you there,
and we are getting dessert. Deal?
♪ Unaware I'm tearin' you asunder
Yeah, yeah, yo ♪
♪ There is thunder in our hearts ♪
♪ It's you and me ♪
We have to turn it off.
We can't. We can't.
No. No. Max is coming back.
We have to.
She's coming back.
♪ Come on, darlin' ♪
Are you okay?
Go.
Okay.
You ready to go home, tourist?
Yeah.
♪ If I only could make a deal with God ♪
♪ I'd get him to swap our places ♪
♪ Be runnin' up that road
Be runnin' up that hill ♪
♪ If I only could make a deal with God ♪
♪ I'd get him to swap our places ♪
♪ Be runnin' up that road
Be runnin' up that hill ♪
♪ Be runnin' up that building ♪
♪ Let's exchange the experience ♪
Lucas.
Holly. Wait.
You can't come with me.
What? What do you mean?
This way leads to me,
to my body, not yours.
You have to find your own way.
How? I don't have Kate Bush.
I don't even know who Kate Bush is.
You don't need Kate Bush
to get out of here.
Turns out, I don't either.
Music isn't the only way back.
You just need something that connects you
to the real world, to home.
Something powerful,
meaningful.
Lucas, when... when he took my hand
in the hospital,
I could feel it. Right here.
But then I could also feel it in here.
But I don't have a boyfriend.
You don't need a boyfriend.
You just need something
that's special to you,
something that makes you feel safe,
something that brings you strength,
something that gives you hope.
Holly the Heroic.
She's here with you now.
But she's also with you in the real world.
Wherever you are,
all you have to do is follow her home.
How?
Just... try and remember
what it is that she means to you.
She doesn't mean anything important.
She's just a toy.
If she's just a toy,
why do you always carry her with you?
Mike.
He said that she had divine powers
and that she never gets scared,
and so if I ever got scared,
I could just... become her.
But I keep trying, and it never works.
No matter what I do, I'm still me.
The girl who needs a stupid night-light.
When my mom was attacked,
I couldn't save her.
I couldn't even save myself.
Holly, get back!
I just stood there.
And then when Henry attacked you...
Stop!
I stood there again.
There's nothing heroic about that.
There was nothing that you could do
in those moments, Holly.
I mean, you're a Wheeler. You're smart.
You honestly think that you could've
stopped those monsters with a fire poker?
And I think you're leaving
a few important things out.
The day that we met,
you went into the woods
even though Henry told you
that dangerous monsters live there.
And then you followed me into the cave
even though you had no good reason
to trust me.
And then when I told you
to go back to Henry,
to go back into danger,
you didn't hesitate.
And today, when I gave up, you didn't.
I've been here for so long, Holly.
So long.
And I could never make it out.
But you?
You found a way through Camazotz.
Because of you...
I get to see my friends.
I get to see Lucas.
You saved me, Holly Wheeler.
You saved me.
So you see,
Holly the Heroic is not just a toy.
She's you, Holly.
She's you.
How did you know that would work?
I didn't.
You still have a long journey ahead.
I don't know where you're gonna wake up.
But I figure Vecna's holding you
in the Upside Down.
But remember, the Upside Down,
it's just like Hawkins.
So find your way back to your house
and hide there.
We will come and find you. Okay?
I'll see you on the other side.
On the other side.
♪ If I only could make a deal with God ♪
♪ I'd get him to swap our places ♪
♪ Be runnin' up that road
Be runnin' up that hill ♪
♪ With no problems ♪
♪ Be runnin' up that road
Be runnin' up that hill ♪
♪ With no problems ♪